Doctor! Are you all right?
博士！你没事吧？
- Yes, I am. I think so.
- Where's Phipps?
- 是的, 没事, 我觉得是 - Phipps 哪儿去了？
He's dead. An Ice Warrior killed him.
他死了, 一个寒冰勇士杀了他！
How did you manage to escape?
你怎么逃出来的？
- The other man helped me.
- Fewsham? I thought he was working for them
- 另外那个人帮了我  - Fewsham？之前我认为他是帮他们的
- He saved my life.
- Doesn't sound much like Fewsham.
- 他救了我的命  - 听起来不像是 Fewsham
- He attacked the Ice Warrior. He's also got T-Mat working again.
- (DOCTOR) Do I gether we can get back to Earth?
- 他袭击了寒冰勇士, 还把 T-Mat 修好了  - 那就是我们可以回地球了？
- I think so.
- Let's not waste any more time!
- 我觉得是  - 那我们不要再浪费时间了！
(Weather Control Center)
（气候控制中心）
（四个推杆上面的文字：DRY - 干燥）
（装置主题文字: Weather Control Unit - 气候控制器)
I had to help them or they would have killed me!
我不得不帮助他们, 否则他们就会杀了我！
All right, Fewsham. There'll be a full inquiry
when we get back to Earth. Tell them.
好了, Fewsham．等我们回到地球, 会有一个完整的听证会的．跟他们说吧
No more time to waste.
We must T-Mat back to Earth immediately.
不要再浪费时间了, 我们必须立即用 T-Mat 传送回地球
But if we all are going, who is going to dispatch us?
但如果我们都走的话, 谁来控制设备送我们走啊
There's a way of doing that. Here, this time switch
delays transportation by ten seconds.
有一个方法可以搞定．这里, 这个延时器可以将传送延迟１０秒
- Oh, I see, how genius.
- I'll dispatch you and follow you using the time switch.
- 哦, 明白了, 很天才  - 我先送你们走, 然后我再用延时器过来
Right, so Zoe, Jamie, come along.
I think this could be quite fun!
好, Zoe, Jamie, 都过来．我觉得这肯定很有意思！
Fewsham, that time switch was down
on the maintenance report for being inoperable.
Fewsham, 维护记录里面说那个延时器已经坏了不能使用
We repaired it!
我们已经修好了
(TRILLING)
In you get, Miss Kelly. I'll use the time switch.
你进去, Kelly 小姐．我后面用延时器过来
You better hurry. Those Ice Warriors will be back any minute.
你最好快点, 那些寒冰勇士随时都可能回来
Do you know, I find T-Mat travel rather disappointing.
知道吗, 我发现 T-Mat 旅行很让人失望
There's no sensation at all!
完全一点感觉都没有
Where have you been? And what were you being up to all this time?
你们去哪儿了？这半天你们都在干什么？
Where's... Miss Kelly! What's happening up there?
哪儿... Kelly 小姐！上面发上了什么？
Will someone tell me what's happening down here?!
有没有谁能告诉我这里发生了什么？
Who are these people? Is T-Mat working?
这些人是谁？T-Mat 能工作了吗？
Now, please, don't... Let us just one question at a time!
好了, 停停, 别... 我们一个个问题来！
Doctor, do you know there's been an alien here?
博士, 你知道这里出现了一个外星人吗？
- An Ice Warrior HERE?!
- Jamie, I am not surprised.
- 这里有了寒冰勇士？！  - Jamie, 我并不奇怪
They have taken over the whole Moonbase.
他们已经完全占领了月球基地
- What about the crew?
- All dead except Fewsham.
- 组员都怎么样了？  - 除了 Fewsham, 都死了
- You left him there?
- He said he'd follow using the time switch.
- 你们把他丢在哪儿了？  - 他说他随后就来, 用延时器
He should be back.
他会回来的
What's happening?
什么情况？
I thought so! The time switch is still out of order.
如我所料, 延时器仍然是坏的
- What? But he said he had repaired it.
- He was lying.
- 什么？但他说他修好了它  - 他在撒谎
- Why?  - Obviously he's working for them!
- 为什么？  - 很显然, 他在为他们做事！
Then why did he let us escape?
那他为什么又让我们逃走？
(HISSING, LABOURED BREATHING)
But don't you see, gentlmen?
你们没看出来吗, 先生们？
The invasion of Moonbase,
the taking over of T-Mat, the seed pods,
入侵月球基地, 占领 T-Mat, 还有这些种子
the arrival of the Ice Warrior,
they're all part of the same plan.
派遣寒冰勇士过来, 这些都是同一计划中的一部分
Plan? What plan?
计划？什么计划？
These incidents seem unrelated.
这些事件看起来都是不相关的
This fungus everywhere, what's that got to do with it?
到处都有的泡沫, 跟这一切又有什么关系？
I'm not quite sure yet. Have your people
been able to make anything of it?
我也还不太确定．你们研究明白一点什么了没有？
It's indestructible. We've attacked it
with every possible way, but without success.
消灭不了它, 我们用尽了各种方法攻击它, 但都没有成效
Yes, but have you tried to UNDERSTAND it?
是, 但你们有没有试过＂了解＂它？
You suggest we should psychoanalyse it, Doctor?
你是说我们应该对它进行心里分析吗, 博士？
I'm merely suggesting that rather than destroy it,
you should find out its composition and purpose.
我只不过是说, 除了消灭它, 你们应该搞明白它的组成和目的
I have some laboratory equipment
in my workshop. You could use that.
我的工作室有一些实验设备, 你可以用
- Good. Then we need a sample.
- No problem about that.
- 很好, 然后我们需要一个样本  - 这没问题
- The gardens are full of the stuff.
- Fine. The let no time to be lost.
- 花园里面到处都是  - 好, 那就抓紧时间吧
I'll get some equipment for you.
我去给你拿些设备
Doctor, do be careful. Those pod things are deadly.
博士, 千万小心．那些夹子很致命的
Don't worry. I've already had experience. I'll be careful.
别担心, 我已经有些经验了, 我会小心的
(DOCTOR) Yes... It's organic.
嗯... 这是有机的
It's alive.
是活的
It's definitely a fungus composition.
这绝对是一种真菌组织
- Are you sure this is correct?
- As far as I can make out, it is.
- 你确定这是对的吗？  - 就我目前的理解, 是的
A molecule of five atoms...absorbs oxygen.
由五个原子组成的一个分子...会吸收氧气
You know, a complete blanket of this
你知道吗, 一大片这样的东西
would reduce the oxygen content
of the Earth's atmosphere drastically.
就会显著降低地球空气中的氧气浓度
According to my calculations,
to one twentieth normal.
根据我的计算, 会降到 5% 的水平
It would make the Earth's atmosphere
uninhabitable to the human race,
这会使得地球的大气不再适合人类居住
but exactly like the atmosphere of Mars!
而是变得跟火星的大气一模一样！
Look at that. Even without vegetation
to feed on, it's still active. Oh!
看这个, 即使不蚕食植物, 它还是活着的．噢！
(ELDRED) If that thing explodes here,
the fumes will kill us! Come on, Doctor!
如果那个东西在这里爆炸, 那种烟会杀死我们的！快闪, 博士！
Just a minute. There must be some way of...
等一下, 肯定有某种方法...
- (ELDRED) Come on!
- (DOCTOR) Sulphuric acid!
- 快点！  - 硫酸！
Hydrochloric acid!
盐酸！
Acetic acid!
乙酸！
(ELDRED) You've done it!
你搞定了！
Well, what was it? What did you throw on it?
哦, 那是什么？你倒了什么东西上去？
- You really think it would work?
- Well It could be less effective than Moonbase, of course.
- 你真的觉得这能行？  - 它可能没有月球基地那么有效, 这也是当然的
which handles up to two million microwave channels simultaneously,
月球基地可以同时支持二百万的微波通道
the satellite would just take a few thousand.
而卫星只能支持几千
That would be enough for vital food supplies.
用来传送重要食物供应那也够了
But we can't use normal communications satellites.
They are not programmed for T-Mat.
但我们不能使用普通的通讯卫星啊, 它们不是为 T-Mat 准备的
No. We have to send up a specially programmed one.
的确不是, 我们得单独发射一颗, 经过特殊编程的
That would mean using a rocket, wouldn't it?
I thought no one use them nowadays.
但那意味着要使用火箭, 对不对？我记得现在都没人使用了？
Not manned rockets, but we do send up satellites for communications.
是没有载人火箭, 但我们还是会用它发射通讯卫星
- How soon can you get one up?
- Well, I don't know. If we're given top priority...
- 多久你们能搞一个上天？  - 嗯, 我不知道．如果我们被授予最高优先级...
(HISSING, LABOURED BREATHING)
There!
那儿！
(FEWSHAM) What is it?
什么东西？
A communications unit from our ship.
一个通讯装置, 可以联系我们的飞船
Connect it to the solar batteries!
把它连到太阳能电池上去
(DOCTOR) Is Commander Radnor there, please?
Radnor 指挥官在, 请问？
- Oh, Zoe, is Radnor there?
- He's in conference with Miss Kelly and Sir James Gregson.
- 哦, Zoe, Radnor 在吗？  - 他正在跟 Kelly 小姐和 James 爵士开会
Oh, I see. Zoe. There's the most wonderful news!
哦, 我知道了, Zoe．现在有一个非常好的消息！
We've found a way of destroying the fungus!
我们找到了一种消灭泡沫的方法！
- Oh! What is it?
- Water! Ordinary water!
- 噢, 什么方法？  - 水！普通水！
- Oh, Doctor, surely...
- There's no time to explain now.
- 哦, 博士, 当然...  - 现在没有时间详细解释了
Apparently, there is a Weather Control Bureau somewhere.
显然, 这里某个地方有一个气象控制局
I want you to get in touch with them.
我期望你去联系一下他们
Can't you reach them on the video phone?
你不能通过视频电话联系他们吗？
No, I've tried. They are not answering,
or it's broken down or something.
不能, 我试过了．他们没接, 或许是什么地方坏了
- What do you want me to do?
- Get hold of the Weather Control Bureau people
- 你期望我做什么  - 联系上气象控制局的人
and to make rain, as much rain as possible
over the entire country!
让他们造雨, 在全国范围内越多的雨越好！
- Well, where is everybody?
- I don't know.
- 咦, 人都哪儿去了  - 我不知道
Let's find the main control room. Come on.
我们先找主控室吧, 快点
So that's why no one answered the video phone.
怪不得没人接视频电话了
And look at that!
快看那个！
No, it's no good. They're locked in position.
不, 这没用, 他们的位置被锁死了
Our fleet is approaching
the gravitational field of the moon.
我们的舰队已经接近月球的引力范围
- Is all prepared?
- Everything is ready.
- 都准备好了吗？  - 都准备好了
I shall guide our ships in on the homing beam signal.
我将用指引信号引导我们的飞船过来
(BEEPING) What the devil's happening?
都什么鬼？
I don't know... Yes, Moon Control!
我不知道... 是了, 月球控制中心！
The sound, can you turn it up?
那个声音, 你能调大一点吗？
Shouldn't we test the directional beam?
我们不测试一下牵引光速吗？
- It is not necessary!
- But it's operating on Moonbase power.
- 这没有必要！  - 但它在耗用月球基地的能量
I can't guarantee the pulsing rate will be the same.
我不能保证脉动率会是一样的
Very well. Test it!
那好, 测试！
Commander Radnor, can this be recorded?
Radnor 指挥官, 能把这录下来吗？
- Yes.  - Quickly! Manage it. It's vital!
- 可以  - 快！安排一下, 这至关重要！
The transmission coming in on the video machine would be recorded.
记录视频系统传送过来的信息
(COMPUTER) Instruction Understood.
Transmission will be recorded.
指令已经收到．信息将会被记录
(TWO-TONE SIGNAL)
(ICE WARRIOR) The device is operating.
设备在运转了
Wait a moment!
等一下！
Um...I must check the connections.
唔...我必须坚持一下连接
(SIGNAL CONTINUES)
If the power fails, we won't be able
to guide the fleet onto the moon.
如果电源失效, 我们就无法引导舰队到月球上了
There must be no failures!
那就必须没有失效！
I realise the importance of that.
If we overshoot the moon,
我明白这个的重要性．如果我们跑偏了
nothing will stop them from going
straight into an orbit around the sun.
他们就会直接进入太阳轨道, 没有什么能拦得住
They will not overshoot!
他们不会跑偏！
Of course not, but since their fuel
supplies are at a marginal level,
当然不会, 但他们的燃料并不是太多
if anything did go wrong,
they'd never be able to regain moon orbit.
如果出现什么意外, 他们无法重新进入月球轨道
This video device is operating!
这个视频设备在运转！
You have betrayed us!
你背叛了我们！
- Every word has been heard on Earth!
- Kill him!
- 每句话都被地球人听到了  - 杀了他！
(TRILLING BUZZ)
(COMPUTER) Countdown in minus three minutes.
三分钟内开始倒计时
Cancel the launch! We can use that
satellite to mislead the Martian fleet!
取消发射！我们可以用那个火箭将火星舰队引开！
Don't you see? Poor Fewsham deliberately
let us overhear their homing signal.
你没明白吗？可怜的 Fewsham 有意让我们听到了他们的引导信号
We can imitate that signal
with a homing device in the satellite!
我们可以用一个引导装置模拟那个信号, 再把引导装置装进火箭里
Commander Radnor, top priority message
to satellite launching site!
我是指挥官 Radnor, 给火箭发射场发送最高优先级的消息！
- Cancel launch! Repeat, Cancel launch!
- (COMPUTER) Message understood.
- 取消发射！重复, 取消发射！  - 消息已收到
If we can deflect their armada, half our battle is won!
如果我们能把他们的舰队引开, 这场仗我们就赢了一半了
- But still, that fungus stuff is everywhere.
- We solved that one with H2O - water!
- 但是, 那些泡沫还是到处都是  - 我们已经发现H2O可以解决那个问题 - 水！
Water? Well, all we need to do is to make it rain!
水？那, 我们唯一要做的就是造雨！